MD TANVIR HASAN

Associate Professor and Co-Director of Centre of Excellence for Urban Equity and Health (CUEH) at BRAC James P Grant School of Public Health, BRAC University

Telephone: (880) -2-9827501-4, ext.6007 (office); E-mail: thasan@bracu.ac.bd

Dr. Md Tanvir Hasan is currently an Associate Professor and Co-Director of Centre of Excellence for Urban Equity and Health (CUEH) at BRAC James P. Grant School of Public Health (JPGSPH), BRAC University. He has more than 9 years of teaching and research experience. He teaches Biostatistics in the Master of Public Health (MPH) Programme at BRAC JPGSPH, BRAC University. Besides teaching, he is currently leading two research projects as Principal Investigator (PI). One of the projects is a nationwide research focuses on the sexual and reproductive health and rights (SRHR) of persons with disabilities in Bangladesh. Another research focuses on managing impact of COVID-19 in Rohingya refugee camps and host communities with culturally appropriate technological solutions. He also Coleads one research project that focuses on formative research, operational research, and baseline-endline study of Disrupting Cross Border Trafficking Networks in Bangladesh. His expertise is in advanced statistical analysis, mixed methods research, implementation research and spatial epidemiological research. His research work mainly focuses on maternal and child health and nutrition, social determinants of health and sexual and reproductive health.

EDUCATION

2013-2017	PhD
	School of Public Health, Faculty of Medicine, the University of Queensland,
	Brisbane, Australia
2003-2004	MS in Applied Statistics, Institute of Statistical Research and Training (ISRT),
	University of Dhaka, Dhaka, Bangladesh
1999-2003	B. Sc. (Honours) in Applied Statistics, Institute of Statistical Research and Training
	(ISRT), University of Dhaka, Dhaka, Bangladesh

CURRENT AND PREVIOUS POSITIONS

2020-present	Associate Professor, BRAC James P Grant School of Public Health (JPGSPH), BRAC
	University, Dhaka, Bangladesh
2017-2020	Assistant Professor, BRAC JPGSPH, BRAC University, Dhaka, Bangladesh
2015	Research Data Analyst, School of Public Health and Social Work, Queensland
	University of Technology (QUT), Brisbane, Australia
2011-2012	Lecturer, BRAC JPGSPH, BRAC University, Dhaka, Bangladesh
2009-2011	Research Associate, BRAC JPGSPH, BRAC University, Dhaka, Bangladesh
2008-2009	Senior Research Assistant, BRAC JPGSPH, BRAC University, Dhaka, Bangladesh

FELLOWSHIPS AND AWARDS

2019	Begum Rokeya Sakhawat Hossain Teaching Excellence Award, JPGSPH, BRAC University, Dhaka, Bangladesh
2012 2016	<i>'</i> .
2013-2016	International Postgraduate Research Scholarship (IPRS), the University of
	Queensland, Brisbane, Australia
2013-2016	Australian Postgraduate Award (APA) living stipend scholarship, the University of
	Queensland, Brisbane, Australia
2003-2004	University of Dhaka merit scholarship, Dhaka, Bangladesh
2000-2004	Institute of Statistical Research and Training (ISRT) merit scholarship, University
	of Dhaka, Dhaka, Bangladesh

RESEARCH GRANTS PARTICIPATION

2020-2023 Managing impact of COVID-19 in Rohingya refugee camps and host communities

	with culturally appropriate technological solutions (CAD 735,100), Principal
2019-2021	Investigator, funded by IDRC, Canada. Formative research, operational research, and baseline-endline study of Disrupting Cross Border Trafficking Networks (Bangladesh) project (USD 98,171), Co- Principal Investigator, funded by Children's Investment Fund Foundation (CIFF).
2018-2020	Sexual and reproductive health and rights (SRHR) of persons with disabilities in Bangladesh (EURO 492,936), Principal Investigator, funded by the Dutch Government.
2019	Exploring the feasibility of collecting a core set of indicators for monitoring and evaluating sexual, reproductive, maternal, newborn, child and adolescent health services and outcomes in humanitarian settings (USD 15,424), Principal Investigator, funded by World Health Organization (WHO).
2018-2019	Feasibility assessment and implementation research for delivering integrated comprehensive SRHR services in Cox's Bazar Bangladesh (USD 86,579), Co- Principal Investigator, funded by World Health Organization (WHO).
2018-2022	Pathways to equitable healthy cities (GBP 374,000), Co-Investigator, funded by Wellcome Trust.
2017-2019	Analytical task in support of capacity development in nutrition surveillance and research (USD 75,000), Co- Principal Investigator, funded by World Bank.
2018	Baseline research for the BRAC ready-made garments workers well-being project (USD 26,885), Principal Investigator, funded by BRAC.
2018	Health care needs and health seeking behaviour among Rohingya refugess in Cox's Bazar: study in selected camps served by BRAC's health care facilities (USD 29,411), Co - Principal Investigator, funded by BRAC.
2011-2012	The role of drug sellers in the informal medical markets: an exploratory study for

TEACHING ACTIVITIES

2010-2011

2017-present	Course Coordinator and Lecturer, Biostatistics (MPH 521), BRAC JPGSPH, BRAC
	University, Dhaka, Bangladesh
2015-2016	Tutor, Practical Regression Analysis (PUBH 7631) and Introduction to
	Biostatistics (PUBH 7630), School of Public Health, the University of
	Queensland, Brisbane, Australia.
2011-2012	Lecturer, Biostatistics (MPH 521), BRAC JPGSPH, BRAC University, Dhaka,
	Bangladesh
2009-2010	Teaching Fellow, Biostatistics (MPH 521), BRAC JPGSPH, BRAC University,
	Dhaka, Bangladesh

effective interventions (USD 135,000 in partnership with icddr, b), Co-Investigator,

Understanding violence against marginalized women in South Asia (EURO 35,000),

PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATIONS

2012-present	Member, Bangladesh Statistical Association
2017-present	Applied Statistics Alumni Association, University of Dhaka
2017-present	The University of Queensland Alumni
2012-2013	Member, Health System Global

funded by Research for Development (R4D).

Co-Investigator, funded by Dutch Government.

ACADEMIC COMMITTEE

2017- present	Member, Academic Committee of MPH Programme, BRAC University
2017- 2018	Member, Self-Assessment Committee for the assessment of MPH Programme,
	BRAC University

PUBLICATIONS (JOURNAL ARTICLES)

Hasan MT, Nath SR, Khan NS, Akram O, Gomes T, Rashid SF. Internalized HIV/AIDS related stigma in a sample of HIV positive people in Bangladesh. *Journal of Health Population and Nutrition* 2012; 30(1): 22-30.

Htike W, Islam MA, **Hasan MT**, Ferdous S, & Rifat M. Factors associated with treatment delay among tuberculosis patients referred from a tertiary hospital in Dhaka city: a cross-sectional study. *Public Health Action* 2013; 3(4): 317-322.

Hasan MT, Muhaddes T, Camellia S, Selim N, Rashid SF. Prevalence and experiences of intimate partner violence against women with disabilities in Bangladesh: Results of an explanatory sequential mixed method study. *Journal of Interpersonal Violence* 2014; 29(17): 3105-3126.

Das J, Das SK, **Hasan MT**, Ahmed S, Ferdous F, Begum R, Chisti MJ, Malek MA, Mamun AA, Faruque ASG. Childhood malnutrition in households with contemporary siblings: a scenario from urban Bangladesh. *European Journal of Clinical Nutrition* 2015; 69(10): 1178-1179.

Hasan MT, Soares Magalhães RJ, Williams GM, Mamun AA. Forecasting the progress towards the target of Millennium Development Goal 1C in children under 5 years of age in Bangladesh. *Public Health Nutrition* 2015; 18(10):1728-1736.

Hasan MT, Soares Magalhães RJ, Williams GM, Mamun AA. The role of maternal education in the 15-year trajectory of malnutrition in children under 5 years of age in Bangladesh. *Maternal and Child Nutrition* 2016; 12(4):929-939.

Hasan MT, Soares Magalhães RJ, Williams GM, Mamun AA. Long term changes in childhood malnutrition is associated with long term changes in maternal body mass index: evidence from Bangladesh, 1996-2011. *American Journal of Clinical Nutrition 2016*; 104(4):1121-1127.

Hoque ME, **Hasan MT**, Rahman M, Long KZ, Mamun AA. Double burden of underweight and overweight among Bangladeshi adults differs between men and women: evidence from a nationally representative survey. *Public Health Nutrition* 2017; 20(12):2183-2190.

Hasan MT, Mamun AA, Williams GM, Soares Magalhães RJ. Spatiotemporal heterogeneity of malnutrition indicators in children under 5 years of age in Bangladesh, 1999–2011. *Public Health Nutrition* 2018; 21(5):857-867.

Ahmed R, Farnaz N, Aktar B, Hassan R, Shafique SB, Ray P, Awal A, Rahman A, Urbaniak V, Kobeissi LH, Rosie J, Say L, **Hasan MT**, Quayyum Z, Rashid SF. Situation analysis for delivering integrated comprehensive sexual and reproductive health services in humanitarian crisis condition for Rohingya refugees in Cox's Bazar, Bangladesh: protocol for a mixed methods study. *BMJ Open* 2019; 9:e028340.

Aktar B, Ahmed R, Hassan R, Farnaz N, Ray P, Awal A, Shafique SB, **Hasan MT**, Quayyum Z, Babaeva M, Kobeissi L, Tahir KE, Chawla S, Rashid SF. Methods applied for collecting information on sensitive sexual and reproductive health (SRH) topic in a complex ecosystem of forced displacement: Case study on a mixed-method research conducted in the refugee camps of Cox's Bazar, Bangladesh. *International Journal of Information, Diversity, & Inclusion (IJIDI)* 2020 (in press).

PUBLICATIONS (BOOK CHAPTER, RESEARCH BRIEF AND REPORTS)

Hasan MT, Khan NS, Akram O, Mahmud I, Lee E, Rashid SF, Nath SR. People Living with HIV Stigma Index Study in Bangladesh. UNAIDS, 2010.

Rashid SF, **Hasan MT**, Camellia S, Muhaddes T, Selim N. Bangladesh Country Report In: Dutta D, Weston M, Bhattacharji J, Mukherji S, Kurien Sj eds. Count me IN! Research Report on Violence against Disabled, Lesbian and Sex-Working Women in Bangladesh, India and Nepal. CREA, 2012.

Aktar B, Ahmed R, **Hasan MT**, Quayyum Z, Rashid SF. Reproductive Health Care in Rohingya Refugee Camps in Humanitarian Crisis in Rohingya Camps: A Health Perspective. Bangladesh Health Watch (2018-2019).

Mridha MK, Hossain M, Hasan MT, Sutradhar I, Kamal SNB, Khan A, Ahmed NU, Khondker R, Mustaphi P, Chowdhury IA, Adams AM and Hyder Z. Investing in Adolescent Girls' Nutrition in

Bangladesh: A Situation Analysis of Trends and ways forward. Health, Nutrition and Population Discussion Paper. World Bank, 2019.

Hasan MT, Chowdhury MW, Amin A, Rashid SF, Rabbani, A. Gender based perception and differentials of COVID-19: Findings from Rapid Surveys. BRAC JPGSPH, BRAC University 2020.